Install IBM Endpoint Manager Agent on AIX Servers.

Installed on the following servers TEPR2E01, daap3p01, dagi3p01, paap3p01, pagi3p01, qaap3p01, tedv2e01, tgdvetl1, tgpretl1

No ipl or reboot of the systemsi required at this time.

Login to the target server and create the following directory if it does not already exist.

 sudo mkdir -p /etc/opt/BESClient 

Mount the soure for the License Tool

 sudo mkdir -p /mnt/ilmt ; sudo mount pgnmsv01:/prod/images/IBM-License-Tool /mnt/ilmt 

Change directory to the latest vesion.

cd /mnt/ilmt/latest

Install the applicaton

 sudo installp -agqYXd  ./BESAgent-9.2.xxx.x.ppc_aixxx.pkg  BESClient 

The results should look like this

	Installation Summary
	--------------------
	Name                        Level           Part        Event       Result
	-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	BESClient                   9.2.1.48        USR         APPLY       SUCCESS
	BESClient                   9.2.1.48        ROOT        APPLY       SUCCESS 

Copy the config file to the location.

 sudo cp -p ./actionsite.afxm /etc/opt/BESClient/actionsite.afxm 

Start the License Tool Client

 sudo /etc/rc.d/rc2.d/SBESClientd start 

Server will reteun the following

 Starting IBM Endpoint Manager: BESClient 

Confirm the application has started sucessfully

ps -aef | grep -v grep | grep BESClient 

If applicatio has started successfully the results should look someting like this

 root  5898376        1   7 13:44:39      -  0:59 /opt/BESClient/bin/BESClient 

Change directory back to your home dicectory and unmount the file system used for installation

 cd $HOME; sudo umount /mnt/ilmt 

Let Rob Michuda know you have installed the software on the server so he can start the monitoring process.

Deinstall IBM Endpoint Manager Agent on AIX Servers.

* You must first stop the agent process before removing it, and you will have to manually remove directories left behind. 

To stop the applicaion

 sudo  /etc/rc.d/rc2.d/SBESClientd stop 

To uninstall the TEM Client on non-Windows systems the simplest method is using the built in package managers

 sudo  installp -u BESClient 

Because this is a non standard IBM Licensed Program Product and does not compleatly deinstall by removing all files it has created you will have to manually remove directories left behind.

 sudo rm -rf /etc/opt/BESClient/ /var/opt/BESClient 

2015 - De-brief notes -- Improvements

Document steps for recovery of TA2 and PTA database disks between backup servers and DB servers.

Step number 16 mkvg command needs more descriptive or improve the script that creates file_systems.txt and update DR documentation. «== Done command added

filesystems.txt needs mkdir -p , modify dr.sh and push to all servers. «==DONE

Improve TZ variable insertion into /etc/profile. Add this into Post install script.

Add a command to check boot list has been set properly

lsvpcfg.sh does not work on XIV , so modify the steps to lsdev -Ccdisk …..

Improve PS1 variable , include it in the Postinstall script

Include the step to configure en1(bck) network to the Post install script.

See if you can automate /etc/hosts into the Post install script.

Include NTP configuration to Postinstall script.

Change the root password & itocroot password, implement it in the Post install script.

Implement ssh passwordless login from nim to all servers, Implement in Post Install script.

Implement /etc/exports within the post install script.

Automate removal of netbackup software – PostInstall script.

SUDO Documentation for Users

sudo or “Super User Do” is an Opensource Unix utility that allows regular users to execute some commands as root on a Unix system.

sudo provides a rich set of features including monitoring, managing and alerting as compared to its competitors like setuid, proprietory RBAC or root equivalent user.

At Tenneco, the following teams use sudo.

DBA Team

Data preservation Team

SAP - Basis Team

HP Openview Team.

Middleware Team

Usage

This is the easiest part. This is as simple as “prefix the command that you need to run as root with sudo”.

For example if a DBA needs to run '/oracle/SID/11203/root.sh' as root during an Oracle installation or upgrade, Instead of jumping to a 'root shell', they can execute the command as folllows

sudo /oracle/SID/11203/root.sh

To list all the commands your user account is entitled to

sudo -l

Dos & Don't(s)

There is no perfect security model. So there are ways around to break everything.

Be responsible. sudo gives great power on a Unix system. “With great power comes great responsibility, visibility and publicity”. Please think before you hit enter on that command you prefixed with sudo. You are Superman !

Use sudo only when needed. It is not to be used for convenience. For example, please do not fix a problem by “chmod 777” because you have the ability to do so. Trust me, it will bite you back.

When in doubt, use “CTRL + C” do not hit enter.

Limitations of sudo

Redirection is one limitation of sudo. For example,

If you need to add something to /etc/motd, a file owned by root. The following code will not work.

sudo echo "something" > /etc/motd

For security reasons, sudo does not permit re-directions. Instead, this works

echo "something" | sudo tee -a /etc/motd

Shell internal commands ..

As an example, “cd” command if used like this, will not work

sudo cd /protected-directory

Instead use

sudo ls -l /protected-directory

i.e. Don't “cd” to the directory. You may wonder, what if I need to “cd” to a directory and create a tar ball with relative paths ? Looking up the man page for tar, I found this

 -C Directory
            Causes the tar command to perform a chdir subroutine to the directory specified by the Directory variable. Using the -C flag allows
            multiple directories that are not related by a close common parent to be archived, using short relative path names.

That means, you can execute this command from wherever you are and it will create a tarball with relative path

sudo tar cvf mytarfile.tar -C /opt/ibm .

sudo audit and logging

All sudo commands are logged and sent to a central repository. Unix team, from time to time , when required , will audit the file for investigation purpose and/or misuse.

Installing PowerCLI on your desktop

If you don't want to install PowerCLI, you can still access it on the storage management server. Jump to the instructions here

From your desktop, click on the start menu and type powershell and then click on Windows PowerShell to open it.

Install the PowerCLI module

Install-Module -Name VMware.PowerCLI -Scope CurrentUser

When prompted to install NuGet provider, type Yes to continue.

Do you want PowerShellGet to install and import the NuGet provider now?
[Y] Yes  [N] No  [S] Suspend  [?] Help (default is "Y"): Yes 

When prompted to install packages from PSGallery, type Yes to continue.

Are you sure you want to install the modules from 'PSGallery'?
[Y] Yes  [A] Yes to All  [N] No  [L] No to All  [S] Suspend  [?] Help (default is "N"): Yes 

If the PowerShell execution policy is restricted, you won't be able to import the module. You can check that by running

get-executionpolicy

Change the powershell execution policy from Restricted to remotesigned.

set-executionpolicy remotesigned -Scope CurrentUser

and when prompted to confirm the change in execution policy type Yes.

Import the VMWare Core Automation Module

Import-Module vmware.vimautomation.core 

And we can safely ignore the warning about joining the VMware Customer Experience Improvement Program.

Set the PowerCLI Configuration to accept invalid certificates. This is needed if your vcenter doesn’t have a valid SSL certificate.

Set-PowerCLIConfiguration -InvalidCertificateAction Prompt 

Try Connecting to the server (When prompted, given your username as YOUR_AD_ID@DRIV.COM & password)

Connect-VIServer cdcvilms156.driv.com 

and you should get a message something similar to below

PS C:\WINDOWS\system32> Connect-VIServer cdcvilms156.driv.com

Name                           Port  User
----                           ----  ----
cdcvilms156.driv.com           443   DRIV\x1naveka


PS C:\WINDOWS\system32>

Verify that you are connected & can run commands

 Get-VMGuest -VM cdcvillx223

and you should see something like this

PS C:\WINDOWS\system32> Get-VMGuest -VM cdcvillx223

State          IPAddress            OSFullName                                    
-----          ---------            ----------                                    
Running        {10.128.114.52}      SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 (64-bit)

PS C:\WINDOWS\system32 

Using PowerCLI to access VCenter from your desktop on PowerShell

Windows provides an integrated scripting environment for PowerShell called Windows PowerShell ISE and it is a very interactive and useful way to create, run and debug commands and scripts.

Click on the Start Menu on your desktop & Search for Windows PowerShell

And, Select Windows Powershell ISE from the list. ISE is interactive and provides various debugging options and is a great tool for exploring VMWare PowerCLI commands. The only thing to be careful while running from the script window is to select only the commands you want to run and click on Run Selection rather than Run. Run will execute all commands in the script, whereas the Run Selection only executes what we have selected.

Connect to VCenter. This can be run from the command prompt or from the script editor.

Connect-VIServer cdcvilms156.driv.com 

When running from the script editor, remember to select the commands that you want to run and press F8 or click on Run Selection

When prompted for certificates, you can click on Accept Permanently to not get this prompt again.

In the Specify Credential window, supply your windows credential that you use to login to VCenter. If connected, it should print the VCenter name and your username

Verify that you can execute commands.

get-vm cdcvillx223

Using PowerCLI to access VCenter from Linux system

Connect to the Storage Management server

ssh pcdcstglxap01 

Switch to sanmontr user

 sudo su - sanmontr 

Invoke the Powershell

 pwsh 

to get an output similar to below.

 [x1naveka@pcdcstglxap01 ~]$ sudo su - sanmontr
Last login: Fri May 21 09:42:03 CDT 2021 on pts/2
[sanmontr@pcdcstglxap01 ~]$ pwsh
PowerShell 7.1.3
Copyright (c) Microsoft Corporation.

https://aka.ms/powershell
Type 'help' to get help.

PS /prod/storageteam/sanmontr> 

Login to the VCenter Server

 connect-viserver cdcvilms156

and login using your windows AD ID & password. Sample snip below

PS /prod/storageteam/sanmontr> connect-viserver cdcvilms156
WARNING: Please consider joining the VMware Customer Experience Improvement Program, 
so you can help us make PowerCLI a better product. You can join using the following command:

Set-PowerCLIConfiguration -Scope User -ParticipateInCEIP $true

Specify Credential
Please specify server credential
User: driv\x1naveka
Password for user driv\x1naveka: ********


Name                           Port  User
----                           ----  ----
cdcvilms156                    443   DRIV\x1naveka

PS /prod/storageteam/sanmontr> 

FTP1.TENNECO.COM User Setup

 After Entitlement creates the user id on the server thwy will send the UNIX Team a ticket to alow the user id FTP access to the server. 
 Make the following changes to the user id substitute actual user name and uid where applicable 
 
 Check the ticket for a Preferred Password. If one is present set the password to that password. 
 If no prefered password is documented, create a complex password and document it so it can be sent to the user. 
 

Change the user shell from /usr/bin/ksh to /usr/sbin/sftp-server

 sudo chuser shell='/usr/sbin/sftp-server' {user login here} 

Change the users home directory from /home/user to /prod/ftp/user

 sudo chuser home='/prod/ftp/{user login here}' {user login here} 

Change the users rlogin to false

sudo  chuser rlogin='false' <user login here> 

Set the users password with specified/ requested on one you have generated and documented

 sudo passwd {user login here}

Set Password to not request change at first login

sudo  pwdadm -c {user login here}

Set the password to not expire

 sudo chuser maxage=0 {user login here) 

Add a group that is unique to this user.

Get the users UID from /etc/password

 sudo  grep {user name} /etc/passwd | awk -F: '{print $3}' 

Set so user can only see his own data

 sudo  mkgroup -'A' id='{UID from step above}' users='{user login here}' {user login here} 

 sudo chuser pgrp='{user login here}' {user login here}

 sudo chuser groups='{user login here}' {user login here} 

Move the users home directory to /prod/ftp

 cd /prod/ftp 

 sudo mv /home/{user login here} . 

Set the users ownership and group permissions

 sudo chown {user login here}:{user login here} {user login here} 

Set the permissions so others can not see or cd to user

sudo chmod 700 {user login here} 

Edit the /etc/ftpusers file and remove the user from the file.

 sudo vi /etc/ftpusers 

Delete the users ID and save the file.

 
 Modify ssh config file to further harden the user id and server Add the user to the appropirate stanza in /etc/ssh/sshd_config 
  - Create a backup copy of sshd_config  where .yn = your initials 

 cd /etc/ssh 

 sudo  cp -p  sshd_config sshd_config-$(date +%Y%m%d-%H:%M:%S).yn 

 sudo vi sshd_config 

Add the username to the end of the stanza “Example of overriding settings on a per-user basis”

Save the file and restart the ssh daemon so the change takes effect

 sudo kill -HUP $(lssrc -a |grep sshd | awk '{print $3}')

 Now test the user id with FileZilla from your pc to insure that the user can access the server as requested. 
 Attach a screen shot of the access from your pc to the ticket as proof of access to the server. 

Install AIX

Setup NIM resources using one of the following ways

A new installation using rte

Build the system using a mksysb of an existing server

Upgrade a mksysb of an existing system on to a new server

Add the server to the console database /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

sudo vi /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

A regular lpar on a P Series frame

taitc118:lpar-ibm:taitc051:taitc118-9111-520-SN10B4F8D:taitc118:2:hscroot

A lpar on a blade IVM VIO Server

dagi3p01:blade-ibm-vio:taprvio9:4:padmin

Open up a console session to the new server. On taitc118 as root

getconsole peerap09

If cloning an existing server, please enter a blackout for the server whose mksysb is being used.

Use this URL to enter a new one

Use this URL to verify the blackout

Power on the server to SMS.

HMC —→ Regular lpars

This code will get the command if we have made proper entries in the console database

grep ^xagi3p02: /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console | awk -F: '{print "ssh "$7"@"$3"\n""chsysstate -r lpar -o on -b sms -m "$4,"-n",$1,"-f",$1}'

IVM —→ IVM guests

This code will get the command if we have made proper entries in the console database

grep ^panmsv02: /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console | awk -F: '{print "ssh "$5"@"$3"\n""chsysstate -r lpar -o on -b sms -n",$1}'

Bladecentre —→ Physical blades

This code will help you with CLI

grep ^taprvio4: /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console | awk -F: '{print "ssh "$5"@"$3"\n""power -on -T blade["$4"]"}'

At the console, setup Remote IPL as normal and perform a network boot.

Wait for the installation to complete

Completely remove network configuration.

Down and detach the active interface

ifconfig $(ifconfig -a | grep : | grep -v lo0 |grep RUNNING | awk '{print $1}' | sed "s;:;;g") down detach

Remove all network device files

for dev in $(lsdev -Ccif | grep ^en | awk '{print $1}' | sed "s;en;;g")
do
   rmdev -dl en${dev}
   rmdev -dl et${dev}
   rmdev -dl ent${dev}
   echo "${dev} removed"
done

Run cfgmgr

cfgmgr

Configure etherchannels if necessary.

LPARs on Blade VIO/IVM servers [ The public network is configured on an etherchannel over the HEAs, The backup network is from the virtualized ethernet - VIOS ]

Create an ether-channel using the HEA adapters

mkdev -c adapter -s pseudo -t ibm_ech -a adapter_names='ent0'  -a backup_adapter='ent1'  -a netaddr='10.32.50.1'  -a num_retries='2' -a retry_time='2'

ent3 Available

Make a note of the 'ent' number. Run cfgmgr

cfgmgr

Also make a note of the ent that is virtualized, the following steps will use these names.

LPARs on a frame that has virtualized Ethernet. [ Both the public and the backup networks are virtualized - in most cases - Use your judgement if an exception was made ]. Make a note of the ent number that has the correct VLAN ids ( Use HMC GUI or CLI ),the following steps will use these names.

Configure IP address.

Configure the front end IP address on the correct interface

/usr/sbin/mktcpip -h <hostname> -a a.b.c.d -m 255.255.255.0 -i enX -g a.b.c.1 -A no -s

Configure the backend(bck) IP address

chdev -l enY -a netaddr=e.f.g.h -a netmask=255.255.255.0 -a state=up

Setup SSH keys for NIM server

Proceed to post install steps

AIX Migration from Version 5.3 to 7.1

Create proper change controls and paper work, get approvals from business, get apps contacts to manage applications etc. As Chris say The whole nine yards

Perform the configuration backup

Login to the respective NIM server ( taitc118 OR penmsv01. Note that taitc118 must be used for all systems other than the systems in Interexion). Define a variable with the target servername.

export nimclient_to="hostname"

Change the hostname accordingly.

Prepare the NIM environment for the migration

sudo nim -o bos_inst -a source=rte -a lpp_source=710TL02-02_lppsrc -a spot=710TL02-02_spot -a no_client_boot=yes -a accept_licenses=yes ${nimclient_to}

For a system outside the Lincolnshire datacentre, do the following

Tweak the NIM to avoid cross atlantic NIM installation

Boot the server to SMS, setup to boot from the local server where we copied the lppsrc and spot.

For a system in the Lincolnshire datacentre, do the following

Boot the server to SMS, setup IPL and perform a NIM boot.

At this menu, change the language to the correct one. set the “Select Editon to standard, and select the right disk

                            Installation and Settings

 Either type 0 and press Enter to install with current settings, or type the
 number of the setting you want to change and press Enter.

    1  System Settings:
         Method of Installation.............Migration
         Disk Where You Want to Install.....hdisk0

    2  Primary Language Environment Settings (AFTER Install):
         Cultural Convention................English (United States)
         Language...........................English (United States)
         Keyboard...........................English (United States)
         Keyboard Type......................Alternate
    3  Security Model.......................Default
    4  More Options  (Software install options)
    5  Select Edition.......................standard
>>> 0  Install with the settings listed above.

                       +-----------------------------------------------------
    88  Help ?         |  WARNING: Base Operating System Installation will
    99  Previous Menu  |destroy or impair recovery of SOME data on the
                       |destination disk hdisk0.
>>> Choice [0]:

At this installation menu, choose 1

                            Migration Installation Confirmation

Disks:  hdisk0
Cultural Convention:  en_US
Language:  en_US
Keyboard:  en_US@alt
Import User Volume Groups:  yes
Enable System Backups to install any system:  yes
Remove Java 1.1.8 Software:  no
Selected Edition:  standard


>>> 1   Continue with Install
                       +-----------------------------------------------------
    88  Help ?         |  WARNING: Base Operating System Installation will
    99  Previous Menu  |destroy or impair recovery of SOME data on the
                       |destination disk hdisk0.
>>> Choice [1]:

At this menu choose 0

                                  Migration Confirmation

  Either type 0 and press Enter to continue the installation, or type the
  number of your choice and press Enter.

    1  List the saved Base System configuration files which will not be
       merged into the system.  These files are saved in /tmp/bos.
    2  List the filesets which will be removed and not replaced.
    3  List directories which will have all current contents removed.
    4  Reboot without migrating.

    Acceptance of license agreements is required before using system.
    You will be prompted to accept after the system reboots.

>>> 0  Continue with the migration.
   88  Help ?

+---------------------------------------------------------------------------
  WARNING: Selected files, directories, and filesets (installable options)
    from the Base System will be removed.  Choose 2 or 3 for more information.


>>> Choice[0]:

Ignore the error like this if installing a system outside of Lincolnshire

nim_rcmd: getaddrinfo: Hostname and service name not provided or found
0042-001 nimclient: processing error encountered on "master":
   0042-006 nimclient: (To_Master) rcmd Error 0

The system reboots after the install. Check the oslevel

oslevel -s
6100-07-05-1228

Restore the SSH host & root keys

sudo YOURID/Pre_Upgrade/aix_upgrade/copy-etcssh-keys.sh

Check the SFTP line on /etc/ssh/sshd_config and fix it. It should be /usr/sbin/sftp-server instead of /usr/libexec/sftp-server

Install any EFIXES on the lppsrc.

For a system outside of the Lincolnshire datacentre do the following

Login to NIM server taitc118, reset the NIM client and de-allocate all resources

nim -F -o reset taerm057
nim -o deallocate -a subclass=all taerm057

Login to the local server where we setup the temporary NFS server and unexport the filesystems

exportfs -u /prod/nim/resources/spot/610TL07-05_spot/usr
exportfs -u /prod/nim/resources/lppsrc/610TL07-05
exportfs -u /export/nim/scripts/taerm057.script

Remove the bootp configuration

cat /etc/bootptab | grep -v ^taerm057 > /var/tmp/bootptab
cp /var/tmp/bootptab /etc/bootptab

Kill the bootpd process

kill $(ps -ef | grep bootpd | grep -v grep | awk '{print $2}')

Inetd will restart it when needed.

Remove the temporary files we copied on taerm055

rm /tftpboot/taerm057.emea.int.tenneco.com
rm /tftpboot/taerm057.emea.int.tenneco.com.info
rm /tftpboot/taerm057.emea.int.tenneco.com.iplrecord
rm /export/nim/scripts/taerm057.script

Login to the NIM server and perform a NIM client cleanup

sudo nim -F -o reset <hostname>
sudo nim -o deallocate -a subclass=all

1. Down load the appropriate HMC Software Upgrade network Images from IBM Fix Central http://www14.software.ibm.com/webapp/set2/sas/f/netinstall/home.html

Down load them using the BULK FTP method to the /prod/images/HMC-Code directory on pgnmsv01. This is the repository for the HMC Upgrade / update software. The Naming convention is straight forward with M0 being the sufix M0 being the initial release. M1 being Service Pack / maintenance level 01 etc. iFixes are noted and grouped under their associated releases. Example V7R7.6M0_iFixes.

2) Back up the HMC

Backup HMC

3. Save the upgrade data - this is an improtant step . This command puts a copy of the saves data on the USB and he disk as well. teh code> saveupgdata -r diskusb </code>

4) Once the HMC hackup has completed log on to the HMC as hscroot. Clear the old log files by entering the following command

 chhmcfs -o f -d 0 

5 Next, run the getupgfiles command to copy the files from the server you downloaded or copied them to over to the bootable disk partition on the HMC. getupgfiles -h hostname -u username -d remote-directory See example below where hostname is pgnmsv01.amer.int.tenneco.com and Directory is prod/images/HMC-Code/V7R7.6.0M0/

 
getupgfiles -h pgnmsv01.amer.int.tenneco.com -u root -d /prod/images/HMC-Code/V7R7.6.0M0/ 

Enter the password for root on pgnmsv01 when prompted. The HMC will return to the command prompt when the file copy has completed. If the file copy fails STOP DO NOT PROCEED !!! You will need to get a PESH password and clear the files and create additional space for the copy.

6. Save the upgrade data - this is an improtant step . This command puts a copy of the saves data on the USB and he disk as well. teh code> saveupgdata -r diskusb </code>

7. Once the files have been copied Enter the following at the HMC command line

 
chhmc -c altdiskboot -s enable --mode upgrade 

8. Finally,reboot the HMC and start the upgrade.

  hmcshutdown -r -t now 

9. The process will take about 45 minutes to complete.

10. Once thje HMC has rebooted, log in to the HMC and apply any and al requored patches for the release.

install-hmc-patchesPpatch HMC

A

Applying VIOS 2.2.5.10 updates from a remotely mounted file system (Power8)

These VIOS levels may be upgrade to ''2.2.5.10''

VIOS 2.1.0.0 VIOS 2.1.0.1 VIOS 2.1.1.0 VIOS 2.1.1.10 VIOS 2.1.2.0 VIOS 2.1.2.10
VIOS 2.1.2.11 VIOS 2.1.2.12 VIOS 2.1.2.13 VIOS 2.1.3.0 VIOS 2.1.3.10 VIOS 2.2.0.0
VIOS 2.2.0.10 VIOS 2.2.0.11 VIOS 2.2.0.12 VIOS 2.2.0.13 VIOS 2.2.1.0 VIOS 2.2.1.1
VIOS 2.2.1.3 VIOS 2.2.1.4 VIOS 2.2.1.5 VIOS 2.2.1.6 VIOS 2.2.1.7 VIOS 2.2.1.8 VIOS 2.2.1.9
VIOS 2.2.2.0 VIOS 2.2.2.1 VIOS 2.2.2.2 VIOS 2.2.2.3 VIOS 2.2.2.4 VIOS 2.2.2.5 VIOS 2.2.2.6
VIOS 2.2.2.70 VIOS 2.2.3.0 VIOS 2.2.3.1 VIOS 2.2.3.2 VIOS 2.2.3.3 VIOS 2.2.3.4 VIOS 2.2.3.50
VIOS 2.2.3.51 VIOS 2.2.3.52 VIOS 2.2.3.60 VIOS 2.2.3.70 VIOS 2.2.4.0 VIOS 2.2.4.10 VIOS 2.2.4.20 
VIOS 2.2.4.21 VIOS 2.2.4.22 VIOS 2.2.4.23 VIOS 2.2.5.0

Make sure you have upgraded the firmware of the LPAR before upgrading the VIOS level

Work to be done prior to the VIOS upgrade

Please ensure that your rootvg contains at least 30GB free space

lsvg rootvg

Login to the host and preserve a copy of rootvg

Power8 Servers are booting from Internal Disks (Mirrored Disks)

Disable the alt_disk_copy script

sudo touch /var/adm/do_not_run_alt_disk_until_removed_tenneco

Make sure that NIM server has a latest copy of mksysb

On the server to be patched, find out the NIM server

grep mksysb /var/adm/.information
mksysbhost:pgnmsv01

In this case, it is pgnmsv01

Login to the NIM server we figured out above, make sure a latest copy of mksysb image backup exists

sudo ls -l /mksysb-images/bos.obj.<hostname>.gz

Check the timestamp on the file, it has to be less than 3 days old. If the mksysb is 3 days old or less Proceed to Step 4

On the server to be upgraded create a new mksysb image. When the command has completed proceed to next step

sudo /usr/local/scripts/mksysb.sh adhoc

On NIM server copy the mksysb image to the repository.

sudo cp -p /mksysb-images/bos.obj.<hostname>.gz /preupgrade/mksysb/

Work to be done during the VIOS upgrade

Create necessary paperwork, secure outages if necessary

Ensure necessary blackouts are in place.

As Power8 VIOS cluster has LPM capability. We will evacuate the frame, by migrating the LPAR one by one. (Please validate first before migrating any LPAR to another Frame)

Check that your alt_disk_copy is bootable Note this is extremely important - do not skip this step this is your backout !!!

Find the altinst_rootvg disk

 lspv | grep altinst_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

 bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command}

Perform a reboot at this time

sudo shutdown -Fr

Verify that the server has booted correctly to the alternate disk.

Reset the bootlist or boot back to the original disk and reboot.

lspv | grep old_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

 bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command}

and boot back to it

sudo shutdown -Fr

Installing the Update Release

There is now a method to verify the VIOS update files before installation. This process requires access to openssl by the 'padmin' User, which can be accomplished by creating a link. To verify the VIOS update files, follow these steps:

Login to the respective VIO server and execute this command.

oem_setup_env

Create a link to openssl

ln -s /usr/bin/openssl /usr/ios/utils/openssl

Verify the link to openssl was created

ls -alL /usr/bin/openssl /usr/ios/utils/openssl

Both files should display similar owner and size and then exit

exit

Create a directory and Mount the remote directory onto the Virtual I/O Server

sudo mkdir -p /mnt/viosupdates

Then

sudo mount 10.0.48.12:/prod/images/vio/vios2/fixpacks /mnt/viosupdates

Login as padmin user and commit previous updates by running the updateios command

sudo su - padmin

updateios -commit

Install the updates by running the updateios command.

updateios -accept -install -dev /mnt/viosupdates/VIOS_FP_2.2.5.10

NOTE: Depending on the VIOs level, one or more of the LPPs below may be reported as “Missing Requisites”, and they may be ignored.

 MISSING REQUISITES:
      
X11.loc.fr_FR.base.lib 4.3.0.0        # Base Level Fileset
bos.INed 6.1.6.0                      # Base Level Fileset
bos.loc.pc.Ja_JP 6.1.0.0              # Base Level Fileset
bos.loc.utf.EN_US 6.1.0.0             # Base Level Fileset
bos.mls.rte 6.1.x.x                   # Base Level Fileset
bos.mls.rte 6.1.9.200                 # Base Level Fileset or #Fileset Update
bos.svprint.rte 6.1.9.200             # Fileset Update

To activate the changes, reboot the VIOS server as user padmin .

shutdown -force -restart

Verify that the update was successful by checking the results of the updateios command and by running the ioslevel command, which should indicate that the ioslevel is now 2.2.5.10.

ioslevel

Accept the license command for all upgrades

license -accept

Commit all the updates

updateios -commit

Work to be done after the VIOS upgrade

Migrate one non production system back and run it for few hours before we migrate all workloads.

Validate the paths are online for all the guests running on that frame

for host in host1 host2 host3
do
   ssh ${host} /usr/local/scripts/chkdsk
done

Capture a snap of the upgraded VIOS system, and send it to IBM to generate iFixes

sudo su - padmin

snap -r

The snap will be stored under /tmp/ibmsupt/snap.pax.Z

Remove blackouts

Upgrading VIOS Servers to VIOS 2.2.6.32

Before installing the Service Release 2.2.6.32 Follow the standard AIX preupgrade steps.

Perform the configuration backup

The update could fail if there is a loaded media repository.

Checking for a loaded media repository

To check for a loaded media repository, and then unload it, follow these steps. To check for loaded images, run the following command:

lsvopt

The Media column lists any loaded media. To unload media images, run the following commands on all Virtual Target Devices that have loaded images.

unloadopt -vtd <file-backed_virtual_optical_device >

To verify that all media are unloaded, run the following command again.

lsvopt

The command output should show No Media for all VTDs.

UPGRADE PROCESS STARTS HERE

Follow the standard AIX preupgrade steps.

Perform the configuration backup

Log in to the VIOS as the user padmin. If you use one or more File Backed Optical Media Repositories, you need to unload media images before you apply the Update Release. If you use Shared Storage Pools(we do not use this), then Shared Storage Pool Services must be stopped.

clstartstop -stop -n <cluster_name> -m <hostname>

Execute oem_setup_env to get out of the restriced shell litations

 oem_setup_env 

 set -o vi 

Chan

Commit previous updates, by running the updateios command.

updateios -commit 

Verify the updates files that were copied, this step can only be performed if the link to openssl was created.

 cp /mnt/ck_sum.bff /home/padmin

 chmod 755 /home/padmin/ck_sum.bff

 ck_sum.bff /mnt 

If there are missing updates or incomplete downloads, an error message is displayed.

Apply the update by running the updateios command.

 updateios -accept -install -dev /mnt

Run the following command to set authorization for padmin.</code>swrole - PAdmin</code>

To load all changes, reboot the VIOS as user padmin .

 shutdown -force -restart

Verify that the update was successful by checking the results of the updateios command and by running the ioslevel command, which should indicate that the ioslevel is now 2.2.2.3.

ioslevel

Run the license acept command for all uprdrates <linense -accept>

Verify that the update was successful by checking the results of the updateios command and by running the ioslevel command, which should indicate that the ioslevel is now 2.2.2.3.

ioslevel

Commit all the updates

updateios -commit